Guide to the Jarratt-Puryear Family Papers, 1807-1918 RL.10120
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jarratt-Puryear family papers
1807-1918, bulk 1843-1879
bulk
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jarratt family
RL.10120
3 Linear Feet 6 boxes, 2,349 items (including 4 vols.)
Collection contains chiefly correspondence relating to the Clingman, Jarratt, Poindexter, and Puryear families, early settlers of Surry County, N.C., together with a genealogical table. Subjects include the slave trade between North Carolina and Alabama, 1830-1835; North Carolina during the Civil War and Reconstruction, conditions at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill prior to the war, plantation accounts, the distillation and sale of whiskey, and business affairs. Correspondents include William James Bingham, John Adams Gilmer, and Zebulon Vance.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical Note
The Clingman, Jarratt, Poindexter, and Puryear families were early settlers of Surry County, North Carolina.
Collection Overview
This collection contains papers of the related Jarratt, Puryear, Clingman, Poindexter and Cash families, and especially of Isaac A. Jarratt, soldier in the War of 1812, landholder, merchant, and distiller.
The collection concerns family matters and local affairs; the education of Mary Jarratt at St. Mary's College, Raleigh, North Carolina; the education of Augustus Jarratt at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, and conditions at the university preceding the Civil War; Isaac Jarratt's partnership with Tyre Glen in the slave trade between Alabama and North Carolina, 1830-1835; the Creek War of 1836; United States relations with Mexico, 1842; a survey of Wilson, North Carolina, 1851. frontier conditions in Texas; the Civil War, including troop movements in North Carolina and Virginia, conditions in the Confederate Army, conscription, lists of absentees, official orders for enrolling new age groups, conscription lists, casualty lists, payments to widows, and home conditions; freedmen, including letters from former slaves inquiring about relatives Jarratt's efforts to get whiskey during the war; North Carolina politics after the war; whiskey taxes; conditions in California; a Texas counterfeit affair in which A. B. Clingman was unjustly suspected; the business affairs of the Jarratt family; the administration of the estates of Samuel L. Davis, William Doss, Sally Doss, and Polly Sapp by Isaac Jarratt and of the estate of Richard Clauselle Puryear (d. 1867) by Jarratt and by his son, Richard Clingman Puryear (b. 1848); and the law practice of Richard Clingman Puryear, including the collection of many claims, 1870-1900.
Volumes include a plantation account book, 1834-1881, containing lists and prices of slaves bought and sold in 1834 and 1835; a plantation account book, 1866-1871, recording supplies and cash advanced to tenants; an administration book, 1845-1848, concerning the estate of Matthew A. Doss; and a ledger, 1869-1870, of Isaac A. Jarratt & Sanderford, a general mercantile firm, containing the records of the sale of whiskey.
Surry County (N.C.) -- History; North Carolina -- Genealogy; Whiskey industry -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Slave trade -- Southern States; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- North Carolina; Plantations -- North Carolina; Vance, Zebulon Baird; Bingham, William James; Gilmer, John Adams; Clingman family; Poindexter family; Jarratt family; University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill -- History; Puryear family
- Jarratt-Puryear family papers, 1807-1918
  - Correspondence, 1807-1849 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1850-1853 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1859-1869 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1870-1918 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 5)
  - Legal papers, 1826-1899 (Box 5)
  - Bills and receipts, 1811-1859 (Box 5)
  - Bills and receipts, 1860-1885 (Box 6)
  - Printed matter, undated (Box 6)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 6)
  - Penmanship exercises, undated (Box 6)
  - Misc. materials, undated (Box 6)
  - Administration book, 1845-1848 (Volume F:1936)
    General note
    Book belonging to Isaac A. Jarratt, Surry County, NC.
  - Ledger, 1869-1870 (Volume L:1937)
    Belonging to Isaac A. Jarratt of Huntsville, Yadkin County, NC. From catalog "Although apparently the records of a mercantile firm, this volume contains little besides records of the sale of whiskey."
  - Account book, 1832-1881 (Volume M:1934)
    Account book of Isaac A. Jarratt, Huntsville, Yadkin County, NC.
  - Account book, 1865-1872 (Volume M:1935)
    Account book of Isaac A. Jarrett, Huntsville, Yadkin County, NC.